[SPEAKER_01]: There's another Ajahn Chah talk, some excerpts.
[SPEAKER_01]: This talk is called Understanding Dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a difficulty in practice, but in anything we undertake, we have to pass through difficulty to reach ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: In dhamma practice, we begin with the truth of dukkha, the pervasive unsatisfactoriness of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as soon as we experience this, we lose heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't want to look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is really the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we want to get around it somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's similar to the way we don't like to look at old people, but prefer to look at those who are young.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we don't want to look at dukkha, we will never understand dukkha, no matter how many births we go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha is a noble truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we allow ourselves to face it, then we will start to seek a way out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Opposing our habits creates some suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally, we are afraid of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If something will make us suffer, we don't want to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We are interested in what appears to be good and beautiful, but we feel that anything involving suffering is bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering is a noble truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is suffering in the heart, it
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it becomes the cause that makes you think about escaping.
[SPEAKER_01]: It leads you to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't sleep so soundly, because you will be intent on investigating, to find out what is really going on, trying to see the causes and the results.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first thing he's saying there is, eh... the first thing you must do, in order to free yourself from suffering, is suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your attitude is all about avoiding suffering, like the non-transparency we discussed before, then you can't free yourself from suffering, because your only concern is to not acknowledge the fact that you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you also have the other way of suffering, but then expecting your
[SPEAKER_00]: Expecting things you do, things you observe, environment, circumstances, your livelihood, you expect those things to sort out your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to suffer, you need to recognize the, well, inevitability of suffering, but then you are the one who must understand that, who must make the effort to understand the nature of it, because that's the only freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like you just miraculously get cured from suffering if you repent long enough, or if you endure the physical suffering, mental suffering long enough, everything falls into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring this suffering that arises on account of restraint and so on, yeah, that is the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that in itself will not result in cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that were so, that's what the Buddha would have said so.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, it's the understanding of the suffering, the arising, the cessation, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what frees you from that suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, eh... that's exactly what Rājan Chah is saying here.
[SPEAKER_00]: If... if you are only concerned about avoiding suffering, maintaining attitude that suffering is bad, you are never gonna, eh... well, acknowledge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acknowledge it as a... as a... as a necessary basis for your liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even... even if you practice for liberation, or you think you are,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not practicing correctly because there is no basis of suffering first.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you put it?
[SPEAKER_00]: All I teach is suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize that people first need to learn how to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the most common attitude with suffering is present is, I must avoid this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must turn away from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, okay, I'll endure this because just going through this suffering will miraculously result in the revelation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: How to recognize suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't need to go seeking out the suffering, because you're already in the position of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is stop distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how to suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or how to recognize that you're already within the domain of suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you do so by recognizing the fact that, like, your own life, your own health, your own youth,
[SPEAKER_00]: People around you, your own investment, your own house, your own things you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine it being taken away tonight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Losing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, see, genuinely contemplate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow those thoughts to arise, to manifest themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, see, are you going to be emotionally perturbed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you going to be affected by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that in itself is already suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, you're not actually suffering in a sense of you lost everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly how people avoid that suffering, by refusing to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you must not think about it, because it's depressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why you can't liberate yourself from what you are liable to, because you stop... you're refusing to acknowledge that you are liable to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, the whole
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything you're doing is maintaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're maintaining yourself, maintaining your family, maintaining your job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you stop...
[SPEAKER_00]: Maintaining is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, why are you maintaining it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the thought, the notion of not having it, makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, so you are...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you're doing is trying to deal with suffering, that at the same time, you're denying it's affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I have nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing bothers me in my life.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, if you don't do anything tomorrow, if there is no burden,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everything you do is in order to avoid suffering, including denial of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do it because you already suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not drowning in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're ready.
[SPEAKER_01]: Drowning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already drowning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not learning how to swim across to the safe shore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you're doing is learning how to basically keep your mouth above the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can sustain that only for so long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sooner or later, you will drown.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha kept talking and giving similes of the crossing the flood, crossing the shore, safety of the other shore and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is the only safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll continue with the Ajahn Chah talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happy people don't develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are asleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a dog that eats its fill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Afterwards, it doesn't want to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can sleep all day.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't bark if a burglar comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too full, too tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you only give it a little food, it'll be alert and await.
[SPEAKER_01]: If someone tries to come sneaking around, it'll jump up and start barking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like what we spoke the other day, like the Spartans, the ancient Spartans.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Spartan children.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentionally, like, underfed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're always alert.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like happy people.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what he means by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what I was saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: People who refuse to acknowledge that even their happiness is under the burden of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: By refusing to acknowledge it, you get to enjoy your happiness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or so it seems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance is bliss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But ignorance is bliss in a sense of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is never...
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is an act of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, as I said before many times, it's not a metaphysical lack of information or mystery.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually your attitude of ignoring, which means, deep down, you know what you're ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why ignorance is undoable, if you make the effort to undo the habit of ignoring certain truths, certain natures of your existence, certain liabilities, certain obviousness of your experience and existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why ignorance and sensuality go hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality provides you distraction, which helps you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction makes your act of ignoring effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because distracts and pleasure is at the end of this distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, me making the effort to ignore what I deep down inside already know, it becomes much easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's ignorance, procrastination, all these things, it's sort of like perpetuating that same attitude of fundamental avidya, of not acknowledging certain truths, not refusing to look at it, pretending it's not there, or
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, you can't pretend it's not there, but then you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I'll deal with it later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, everybody dies.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll deal with it when my time comes, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, even if you stop and reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wait a minute.
[SPEAKER_00]: My whole life is about avoiding this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here I am, holding a magical belief that suddenly, when it comes after 50, 60 years on this earth, I'll be able to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, while I could deal with it, I was refusing to deal with it, because it was too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's too unpleasant to think about death when you're alive, and somehow, you maintain a notion that you'll be able to deal with it when it's actually occurring?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's unpleasant to think about it, you can only imagine how unpleasant it's going to be when it's actually there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll continue with Ajahn Chah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we speak the subtle dhamma, most people will be frightened by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They won't dare to enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even saying, don't do evil, most people can't follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I've sought all kinds of means to get this across.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing I often say is, no matter if we are delighted or upset, happy or suffering, shedding tears or singing songs, never mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Living in this world, we are in a cage.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't get beyond this condition of being in a cage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you are rich, you are living in a cage.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are poor, you're living in a cage.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're burdened by the same liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you watch a movie, you're watching it in a cage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's exactly what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to realize that your happiness, watching a movie, family, successful business, is within the burden of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are caged by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like, oh, there's no happiness, everything is depressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there is, but you have to look at the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Happiness or grief, it's within the burden of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's within the liability of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you maintain the attitude of ignoring that problem, through taking that happiness for granted, which then means you will be taking avoiding of any grief and suffering for granted as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: What, what is this cage?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is the cage of birth, aging, illness, death.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this way, we are imprisoned in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't know what we really are or what we are doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, we are all doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: All we are doing is accumulating suffering for ourselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something far away that causes our suffering, but we don't look at ourselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: However much happiness and comfort we may have, having been born, we cannot avoid aging.
[SPEAKER_01]: We must fall ill and we must die.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is dukkha itself, here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liability of your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... there's absolutely no alternative to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only alternative is to free yourself from it or to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is some excerpts from a Ajahn Chah dhamma talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called, It Can Be Done.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is about halfway through the talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nibbāna pācchayo bhūtu.
[SPEAKER_01]: One need not aim at anything or wish for anything at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just aim for nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: All manner of becoming and birth, merit and virtue in the worldly way, do not reach there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Making merit and skillful karma, hoping it will cause us to attain to some better state,
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't need to be wishing for a lot of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just aim directly for nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting sīla, wanting tranquility, we just end up in the same old place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessary to desire these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: We should just wish for the place of cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most important point is that while we have life, we should train the mind to be even in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_01]: We should be able to share wealth and possessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the time comes, we should give a portion to those in need.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as if we were giving things to our own children.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sharing things like this, we will feel happy and we can give away all our wealth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, whenever our breath may stop, there will be no attachment or anxiety, because everything is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha taught to die before you die.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be finished with things before they are finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can be at ease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let things break before they are broken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let them finish before they are finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the Buddha's intention in teaching the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you listen to the teachings for a hundred or a thousand eons, if you do not understand these points, you won't be able to undo your suffering and you will not find peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not see the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But understanding these things according to the Buddha's intention and being able to resolve
[SPEAKER_01]: This view of things is called Sīma Dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: This view of things can make an end of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can relieve all heat and distress.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whoever strives sincerely and is diligent in practice, who can endure, who trains and develops himself to the full measure, those persons will attain to peace and cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever they stay, they will have no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether they are young or old, they will be free of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever the situation, whatever work they have to perform, they will have no suffering, because their minds have reached the place where suffering is exhausted, where there is peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... the teaching is simply aim at nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to understand what that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to aim at something, you need to know what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was gonna say, but I decided to let you finish.
[SPEAKER_00]: That bit where it says, like, you want it, means you must know at least where to look for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must have some understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a problem for most people, especially when they start the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of... Well, you start with, like, non-understanding of what nibbāna is, of course, but you continue
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you start making efforts, but none of those efforts are actually aimed at clarifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, hold on, let me get the idea at least what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through getting the idea, you get to know what it is and what you can do about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for most people, they expect nibbāna to happen on account of, you know, their commitment to the meditation technique or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: They expect nibbāna to occur and then all my problems will be will be gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nibbāna is about undoing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They make you liable to problems, they make you liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is not just a replacement, just a new novelty experience that replaces everything, overrides everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is the experience in a sense of when you undone, when you have undone all the unwholesome, all your desire, all your ill-will, all your attitude of distraction and delusion,
[SPEAKER_00]: That negative experience that's left as a result of that undoing, that's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when nibbāna is also a dhamma, a phenomena, but it's asankhata dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's undetermined by any greed aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people will be better off when they start practicing to think... to spend the time thinking about dhamma, than practicing their mindfulness of... sorry, think about dhamma and nibbāna, than practice their mindfulness of breathing or something, which is going to be some mechanical physical technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect on...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is... what does the Buddha say nibbāna is?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... from a point of view of somebody who started the practice, what is the other thing that you could say it's a cessation?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is nibbāna closer, based on the Buddha's description, to what you have the idea that death is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it closer to some kind of transcendental astral projection realm of your liberation?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's closer to death, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because nibbāna is against the grain of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the other thing that's against the grain of life?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people would freak out in the suttas, when they would understand nibbāna, when the Buddha would teach.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they would say, oh, well, that will kill me, that will destroy me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they would despair and start pulling their hair and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like full-on existential dread.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize... and the only reason you fear death, fear nibbāna, is because you refuse to give up your possession of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to give up your life, as in you don't have to go and kill yourself to attain nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's nonsense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you must give away the possession of your life, which for most people equates death, which is why it's so frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Die before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Ajahn Chah said, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Die before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is closer to the death from Putujana's point of view, than anything else is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the Buddha himself was teaching maraṇasati as the quickest, sharpest way for enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplation of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a bit too sharp for some people.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he mellowed it out a bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, that's exactly why.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it directly results in liberation, if you do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also why, like, it said, which is, you know, I know people mystified, but it's, you know, in the suttas, where it said, like, somebody develops the right view, but they haven't reached the fruits of it yet, they don't do it, they do it at the moment of the death, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's almost like a mystical, always, in the moment of the death, you get this light revelation.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reach the fruits of your right view, for example, or your arahantship, at the moment of your death, because that's when nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your right view has already understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has been preventing you, maybe you were not as diligent as you should have been, but once you're going through the experience of dying, what you're going to have with yourself there, is only your right view, or wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you haven't developed the right view during the life, that's why, when death comes, it's too late to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you say, your view is there for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you have there, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when your right view is right there, that's why, oh, he gets his enlightenment or becomes an arahant at the moment of dying, as in when he's dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what nibbāna is, for a living mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation of aggression.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now he's there with the right view, not with a vijja.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it would be different for him, because he made the effort while he was still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: He died before he died.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... you fully remove any possessiveness, any... like, make sure everything ceases, in the sense of not you go around destroying things, but you destroy your emotional dependence upon things, including your own life, your own health, your own youth, your own family, everything, everything, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: You emulate death.
[SPEAKER_00]: When death comes, I can't even conceive a second longer holding on to these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we also must know, you don't have to destroy the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just fully develop that theme of being unable to hold on to this, if it decides to go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if destruction of things, if throwing away your possessions, frees you from possessions, then, as I said, all you have to do is take away this life to get nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't work like that, doesn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need this life in order to understand nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might be throwing away your possessions to simplify your life to an extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you think that throwing away your possessions is bringing you closer to nibbāna, well, you're seriously deluded.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize possessions are not... your possession is not in things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your attitude towards the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something you can't throw away.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the ultimate possession of the views, and the wrong views, or the right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your possession of the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will die before you die, means you make sure you have removed any appropriation, any sense of ownership in regard to your experience as a whole, whatever the content of that experience is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when the experience of death comes, well, there's nothing there that contradicts it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no assumption of possession, appropriation, control, that will be directly at odds with the experience of death, which denies it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're at peace, even in death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, it's not your death.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not being one destroyed by that death, because you're not there to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or like what Ajahn Chah says, be finished before it's finished.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, sure, sure, exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Finish the thing before they are finished, because they are going to be finished, for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a... for an arahant who is finished, who is in nibbāna, death is parinibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not even death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha wouldn't even use the word death for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would say the aggregates break apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wouldn't use the same Pali word for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for Putujanā, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He dies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, you don't die because your aggregates break apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: You die because the aggregates break apart that you are appropriating them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're appropriating them and they break apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, arahant cannot prevent five aggregates from breaking apart, cannot prevent body from withering away and dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that's truly what death is, as in the mere destruction of the body, then nobody can be free from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the appropriation of that which will be destructed, destroyed by the death or accident or old age or illness, sickness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That appropriation makes it death, aging and sickness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without it, it isn't.
It's just a falling apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... you can designate whichever way you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: My cup has died.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just basically a change, cessation of this, something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there is no appropriation, means none of it will be yours, which means you are done in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, this is obviously much subtler thing, harder thing to see, and it's much easier to just either deny your life, deny your possessions, throw everything away, burn your house, must not own anything, must not help anyone, because everything is attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind is the attachment, not things you get attached to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you change your mind of being... from being mind of attachment to mind of non-attachment, everything else can stay the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Except, of course, the basic virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: That needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, certain amount of engagement with the world, in an unwholesome sense, must be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, everything else...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the Buddha himself would have stayed in the king's palaces and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if that's how you measure the attachment, it means he was extremely attached.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a ridiculous thing to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that doesn't mean, also, I can go and stay in the palaces.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, are you the Buddha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you an Arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, well, you have to be careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're careful, in a sense, you have to see what is it that makes it wholesome or unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it that makes it, it doesn't matter if I stay in King's Palace, or what is it that matters?
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I'm becoming attached to staying in King's Palace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you aware of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are, then, yeah, you probably won't be affected wherever you stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be at ease, as Ajahn Chah says.
[SPEAKER_00]: By things coming, going, having, losing, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, your mind becomes even.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, even, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nibbāna being non-greed, non-hatred, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we can develop this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through clarifying what greed, what desire for sensual pleasures and so on is, you get to discern what non-greed is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I'm greedy for something,
[SPEAKER_01]: I can acknowledge that, and not engage in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, your body needs to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not habitually just giving in to it, even before you recognize the thought being present, intention towards those things present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you're physically restrained, then, yeah, you can start noticing it on the level of your mind, and then you realize, okay, these thoughts have arisen on their own, but I'm not obliged to say yes to the desire that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to try and get rid of it, because it wasn't my doing in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't create this desire in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I can certainly...
[SPEAKER_00]: I am certainly responsible if I choose to welcome it, if I choose to entertain it, if I choose to think further upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's better of the... rather than, like, sitting and trying to get experience from meditation, sit quietly and make a meditation about experience of understanding what these things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where the peace is.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're not affected by your thoughts changing, when you're not affected by the desire arising, or disagreeable displeasure arising, or boredom arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't affect you, means you don't have to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't act out of it, you stop perpetuating the very things that prevent you from experiencing nibbāna, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if you do that for one hour... Yeah, you do that for one hour, but it wasn't the hour of kind of mindless sort of head nodding...
[SPEAKER_01]: Flawed meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Flawed meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said before, it's an hour of clarifying the meaning of these mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, even when you're not in your meditation then, when you go about your life, at the back of your mind, those themes are still going to be present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you start to meditate, regardless of your posture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not I'm meditating, I'm meditating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just develop the theme, establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upon the perception of the non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, perception of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: All those
[SPEAKER_00]: Meditations that the Buddha talks about in the suttas are basically themes upon which you can establish your mind if you spend long enough time dwelling on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: His mind turns towards it, inclines, he doesn't turn towards company, because he's been thinking about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what he starts to value.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he values it, he establishes himself upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, nothing inferior to those states can disturb him.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like it, the theme, the theme of nibbāna, making your life... Oh, nibbāna is just like, wow, it's so... why is it unattainable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of greed, aversion, delusion, that's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just start looking at how much percentage of your daily life
[SPEAKER_00]: You spend cultivating desire, welcoming it, being careless about it, ill-will, distraction, oh, I'm bored, I'm gonna do this, I'm gonna read this, I'm gonna watch that, I'm gonna go and talk to these people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, oh no, if I were to stop doing these things, rooted in desire, rooted in ill-will, rooted in delusion and distraction, that brings me closer to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's closer to what nibbāna is than anything else I do on top of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's going become a monk for 60 years and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do that on top of your greed, aversion, delusion, you're not a step closer to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just by doing that, refraining from those unwholesome things, then it doesn't really matter what...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your life will form around it, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you become a monk or not, that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's not the point, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But things will start to form around your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will go hang around monasteries, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you might not hang around, depending on the monastery, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, the point is, your mind will be then inclining towards things that the Buddha was describing as the mind will be inclining to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion, non-company, renunciation, release, finding basically joy in that solitude, in that non-engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you're afraid of engagement or you don't know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because you're contemplating the theme of nibbāna which naturally results in this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when engagement comes, it won't bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will certainly not try to make it stay longer because you're actually bored on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, quite the contrary.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do it as a sense of duty, you have no problem with that, but you won't be doing it a second longer, for any other reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha meant, says, when the... when the... like a monk whose mind is inclined towards nibbāna, seclusion practice, when he's visited by kings and retinues and other people, he would just say enough to answer their questions, but not a word longer to make them kind of linger or stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... yeah, you don't want them there, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want anyone, anywhere around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion kind of ties in with that whole idea of cessation and renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that automatically, just by locking yourself alone in the room, you're suddenly practicing seclusion of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seclusion of greed... seclusion from your own mind of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That then gets sort of exemplified with also physical seclusion and all these other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, physical seclusion can help you, but don't mistake that to be like this seclusion that results in liberation of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, one thing for sure, company will not help either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless it's a company of somebody with the right view or higher, but then, in that case, they wouldn't want to have you near them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would they associate with a Bhutujana?
[SPEAKER_01]: You've just got to be honest with yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this causing more greed?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I going for this now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it because I'm just trying to, like, get away from stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: What stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the stuff I'm trying to get away unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, if it's unwholesome, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just wanted to get away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's not unwholesome, then why am I trying to get away from it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I bothered by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to realize that the responsibility for your own suffering is only on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means responsibility from liberation of your own suffering will be also on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Circumstances do not make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your own attitude, in regard to circumstances, that makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is another... Well, we're still from that talk, It Can Be Done, Adin Shah.
[SPEAKER_01]: A few more excerpts.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is from the beginning of the talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it comes to taking precepts, for example, a monk will proclaim the precepts and the lay people will vow to undertake them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't misunderstand what is going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The truth is that morality is not something that can be given.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can't really be requested or received from someone.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can't give it to someone else.
[SPEAKER_01]: In our vernacular, we hear people say, the venerable monk gave the precepts and we received the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: We talk like this here in the countryside, and so it has become our habitual way of understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we think like like this, that we come to receive precepts from the monks or on the lunar observance days, and that if the monks won't give the precepts, then we don't have morality, that is only a tradition of delusion that that we have inherited from our ancestors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking in this way means that we give up our own responsibility
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having firm trust and conviction in ourselves, then it gets passed down to the next generation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they too come to receive precepts from the monk... to receive precepts from the monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the monks come to believe that they are the ones who give the precepts to the laity.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, morality and precepts are not like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not something to be given or received.
[SPEAKER_01]: In truth, morality resides with the intentions of people.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we have the conscious determination to refrain from harmful activities and wrongdoing by way of body speech, then morality is coming about within you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should know it within yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is okay to take the vows with another person.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also recollect the precepts by yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know what they are, then you can request them from someone else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something very complicated or distant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So really,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever we wish to receive morality and dhamma, we have them right here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is just like the air that surrounds us everywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever we breathe, we take it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: All manner of good and evil is like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we wish to do good, we can do it anywhere, at any time.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can do it alone or together with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Evil is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can do it with a large or small group, in a hidden or open place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's kind of self-explanatory, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about, again, it's about don't project responsibility for your own virtue and morality on the external form that you can use to learn from or to remind you of it, but ultimately it's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, if you haven't had the chance to formally take the precepts in the monastery, it's simply completely unrelatable to whether you keep the precepts or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one making the magical connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I can't be moral now, because I haven't recited it in front of a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recite it to remind yourself what you should be doing, whether you recite or not, which is to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five precepts is what Buddha said distinguishes humans from animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll continue a little bit there, because what you just said now... Ajahn Chah says that morality, this is something that we should consider normal for all humans to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person who has no morality is no different from an animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you decide to live like an animal, then, of course, there is no good or evil for you, because an animal doesn't have any knowledge of such things.
[SPEAKER_01]: A cat catches mice, but we don't say it is doing evil, because it has no concept of knowledge of good or bad, right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: These beings are outside the circle of human beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is the animal realm.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha pointed out that this group is just living according to the animal kind of actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those who understand right and wrong, good and evil, are humans.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha taught this dhamma for humans.
[SPEAKER_01]: If we... if we people don't have morality and knowledge of these things, then we are not much different from animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is appropriate that... appropriate that we study and learn about them and... and make ourselves able.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is taking advantage of the precious accomplishment of human existence and bringing it to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as we said just a few minutes ago, it's nothing...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you might have to do it initially, learn about it, take that kind of formal sense, but you recognize it's about your day-to-day life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about what goes on in your mind throughout day-to-day life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: But watch your mind for what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Watch your mind for unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you do about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You try to get rid of it, the level of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that kind of implies you're in control of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're in control of what arises in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have say in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But do you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not according to the Buddha, whereby mind and the thoughts is just another sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind wants to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eyes want to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you realize, okay, so what is on me then?
[SPEAKER_00]: When thoughts of desire or thoughts of ill will present themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is on me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the line there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to which I'm responsible, before or after which I might not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these reflections is something people don't usually do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to be told what to do, told where to focus, told what to read, if anything, and things will fall into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no falling into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you building a place and then putting things there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Manly effort, manly strength,
[SPEAKER_00]: Manly determination, as the suttas would often describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ask yourself, throughout your day life, okay, so... Is my mind affected by desire now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are there things that I'm... maybe I don't want right now, but I might think about something I want later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I want it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it for my benefit, for benefit of others?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whose benefit?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the result of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it genuine benefit to to my livelihood, to my health?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it just a distraction and pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, sometimes it can be mixed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so it's for my health, but it also... Are there alternatives for my health that will not necessarily be as pleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I be affected if, say, I go for those alternatives, but I don't go for the alternatives of pleasure that I want?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you ask yourself, will I be emotionally disturbed if I don't get the pleasure I want?
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, you don't go for that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next time, you might not be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to be honest with yourself and transparent, so that these questions can start to apply.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I keep saying, like, don't necessarily rush to give the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not about the answer, it's about becoming a question yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's how you start to question your own existential attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like the expression, like, oh, let that sink in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, don't rush, just let it sink in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You bring out the theme through a question, but you don't rush answering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even for a day or two, let it be on your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a theme you're developing for a day or two.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a form of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sinking in, that particular thing you're reflecting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I prefer this over that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I fear this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is this a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, it all comes down to, am I emotionally affected by these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I... does this pleasure, emotionally, make me angry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Make me lash out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does pleasure, emotionally, make me crave for it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Make me go for sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does neutral feeling, emotionally, make me sort of just turn to oblivion and distraction?
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, you don't cultivate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean you try to get rid of everything and stop everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize responsibility is not for the thoughts that have a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Responsibility is for acting out of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: For welcoming it, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: For entertaining it, as the Buddha described so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But many people would think, okay, so I must not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must stop thinking this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not think this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have thoughts of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must stop thinking that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you must stop indulging that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you must also stop trying to get rid of it in a sense of the you are the master controller of it in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that becomes your form of engagement with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to negate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you remain bound to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it wasn't your doing, the arising of those thoughts
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in order to arrive at the point where you can start seeing those thoughts in your mind like that, you must have... you must develop virtue and, like, restrain your physical actions and your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you must toughen up, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that restraint and renunciation, you must develop some standards that you're able to withhold the pain, withhold discomfort, without acting out of it right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sensuality is uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why... that's why it's so... it's so... so enchanting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because not just that you avoid the initial hit of discomfort of not getting the sensuality you want, but the underlying provides you with pleasure on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it feels like win-win.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because fundamentally, you still act out of trying to avoid the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill-will is uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not able to hold it without acting, without saying something, how can you then see your thoughts being entertained in regard to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to toughen up.
[SPEAKER_00]: By toughening up, you develop confidence that you know you won't be acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you leave yourself no other choice, but to deal with the suffering that you have trapped and enclosed within yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the first bits of the... the first talk you read from Ajahn Chah today, was that you must learn how to suffer, and then you'll know what to do, or how to do about suffering, how to go about suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, throughout the day, just keep reflecting, keep asking yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're engaged in certain actions right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is this rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, let that question then endure there a bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this sensual?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Carelessness?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would happen if I suddenly... this stops?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, whatever I'm doing gets taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be flustered?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be affected?
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean you have to go and destroy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means you always have to be aware of what effect might have on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you get to learn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll read a short verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's related.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: In terms of striving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying toughen up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to toughen up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's from the Therigata, 3.5, by a disciple of the Buddha named Matanga, the son of Matanga.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, his verse...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too cold, too hot, too late, they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the young neglect their work like this, opportunities pass them by.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one who considers hot and cold as nothing more than blades of grass, he does his manly duty and his happiness never fails.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: With my chest, with my chest I'll fuss aside the grasses, vines and creepers and foster seclusion.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, we spoke about it many times before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, modern world, especially Western world,
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think it's too different, but... yeah, everything, everything is wanted on easy terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is wanted on my own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people think, oh, they had all the luck being born in the time of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there was a bit of luck, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: They were never too hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not, yeah, that's not why they were lucky.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were lucky because the circumstances were harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: were optimal, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not harder in a sense they were tortured, but harder in a sense they could have not be existentially spoiled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take things for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality proliferated left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they were lucky.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the time was optimal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were kept in check by circumstances, the mind could not have proliferated, which means it wasn't as polluted as the minds today are, on average.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, today, in order for people to understand, they need to do much more self-induced pollution that they've been cultivating throughout their life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through education, relationship, everything else, you just keep adding to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could also see, like, just from the point of view of that, like, toughen up with mental toughness or being able to withhold the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: On average, how much softer we are today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Much, much softer.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, back in the day, you know, like, you lose your whole family in a flood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Six of your eight children die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, it's just like not being able to have a child.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need 20 years of counseling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not to have dinner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't get enough food.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get enough breakfast and lunch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, actually, nobody, like, in certain in the Western world, everybody gets enough food.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, well, most people get enough food, but it's more like, not as much as you used to, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, those are the little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, like, you start reflecting, like, why am I frightened in the prospect of this?
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember when I, when I started reading the, the suttas and then the idea, okay, renunciation and precepts, and I was like, I want to do the fasting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no fasting even, like, I'll never eat or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, I'll skip a dinner today, and I'll get this, like, anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'll go to bed hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I was only about 16, 17.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, I'm thinking, you're not gonna die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You ate twice that day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just decide to skip the habit of dinner.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my mind was freaking out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fortunately, for me, with my own views at the time, I saw that as a challenge that I must overcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people would not necessarily think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would think, okay, no, I'll just go and eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: I shouldn't be doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you will get so frightened just by not shoving enough... not shoving the same amount of food in your mouth, which is more than enough, even what you already ate, for sustenance, macronutrients, everything is already covered, yet you're still freaking out for not eating what you're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean you're existentially spoiled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the threshold of what you deem is necessary is far too inflated than what actually is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, yes, circumstances simplification of many things in today modern life is... it's more likely going to result in good than in bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if they don't take it further, in terms of practice, dhamma and everything else, it's certainly gonna prevent depression and all sorts of modern ailments that kind of plague the Western world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything bothers you, because you're too soft.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the guidelines, the precepts, they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can find them easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just take those on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's been around even after, you know, not necessarily like in Stoicism and all these other...
[SPEAKER_00]: It was the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: People realize that if you start to, like, practice the degree of self-restraint, you develop certain strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the whole apathy, the word apathy from apatheia, the Greek, I think it's Greek, Latin, Greek, literally means indifferent, means equanimous, means even in regard to anything that comes your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, of course, there is the ultimate evenness of arahantship, but even the relative evenness is a good place to start or something to strive for.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were those suttas where the Buddha described those two kingdoms and said why this kingdom will always win is because they sleep on wooden pillows, they bathe in cold water, they're like... Wake up before the sun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wake up before the sun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're always vigilant, live on that kind of physical hardship to a degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which keeps them sharp.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, Puthujana cannot necessarily decide or make myself wise or I prevent myself from proliferating.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Puthujana can certainly recognize that circumstances can play the part in his mind proliferating towards sensuality or real will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, he prevents the circumstances from spoiling him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what those kingdoms, they would always win, do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those were the values that they cherished.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you put them in the environment of getting after the sun, bathing with soft, nice, scented, warm water, they will go the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Human mind is the human mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Universal nature is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you recognize the circumstances, so you prevent yourself from ending up in that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's not my fault that soft... that warm water makes me soft.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not my fault that soft pillow makes me... makes me lazy in the morning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not your fault that softness of your pillow results in softness of your body, but it's your fault to choose that, that will then result in the softness of your body, and being unable to bear the elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for most... a lot of people don't even know about these things nowadays.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's like it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, see, it's not exactly like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when I started, I wasn't even necessarily just directly naming suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was very early, the first days of reading anything, like meditation and philosophy and spiritual things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first conclusion, it's like, oh, self-restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't be smoking, drinking, going around, partying and expect, like, to develop mental... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just the most natural, immediate conclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which I think many people have at the back of their mind, but they might, you know, go at great lengths to cover it up and then try to sort of twist and bend and have it all, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be a layman, enjoy enjoy sensuality and everything and be an arahant at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wish you all the best with that.